<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: projects | Georgetech]]></title>
  <link href="http://georgebonnr.github.io/techwritings/blog/categories/projects/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://georgebonnr.github.io/techwritings/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-28T14:20:25-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://georgebonnr.github.io/techwritings/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[George Bonner]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I Just Presented as a Finalist at LAUNCH Hackathon]]></title>
    <link href="http://georgebonnr.github.io/techwritings/blog/2013/11/11/i-just-presented-at-launch-hackathon/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-11T16:33:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://georgebonnr.github.io/techwritings/blog/2013/11/11/i-just-presented-at-launch-hackathon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I had no idea my first hackathon experience would be so awesome, fun, and educational.</p>

<p>Here are a few specific things I learned from this weekend:</p>

<h3>1. Great ideas can come from the unlikeliest places.</h3>

<p>Our team came into Friday evening with an idea that we hatched almost as a joke: in-store scavenger hunts. We had nothing to lose, 48 hours to kill, and an idea that made us chuckle. As we iterated on our idea, we realized that anything that genuinely makes shopping fun has big potential. Some of the people that looked at our app thought the same thing.</p>

<br>


<h3>2. Ideas are still valuable</h3>

<p>The prevailing opinion in tech recently is to value great execution over great ideas. To be successful at the highest level you need both, but for proof-of-concept apps there&rsquo;s still room to dream big and deliver an app that, while it might not be perfectly executed, is both usable and functional.  Which brings me to the next thing I learned&hellip;</p>

<br>


<h3>3. Get. It. Done.</h3>

<p>A surprising amount of teams give up, lose interest, or aren&rsquo;t able to finish their ideas in time.  Even at LAUNCH, which vets its developers  closely (they mentioned that they had rejected 2 out of every 3 applicants to the event), a significant amount of the teams didn&rsquo;t finish.</p>

<p>Since our team didn&rsquo;t have much time to plan prior to the event, finishing our app the in the time allotted was definitely not a foregone conclusion. The fact that we didn&rsquo;t have anybody with professional design experience also made things a bit more difficult. By the time we were done, each of us had encountered &ldquo;make it work&rdquo; moments where we had to use a piece of tech in an unexpected way or learn something new about the tools we were using.</p>

<p>As it turns out, by Sunday evening we had a fully functional app utilizing Node, Firebase, Facebook authentication, 3 separate Kohl&rsquo;s APIs, Angular on the front end, and a responsive design delivering a solid user experience via a mobile web app. It wasn&rsquo;t pixel-perfect, but it was attractive, usable, and bug-free. And most of all it was finished. Whatever your idea is, finish something.</p>

<br>


<h3>4. Practice your pitch.</h3>

<p>We practiced our pitch 2-3 times before presenting to the first-round judging panel, and it paid off. We each got to talk, and we communicated our idea in a compelling way. I don&rsquo;t think we would have wound up on stage at the end of the night if we hadn&rsquo;t put in the time to refine our pitch before we showed our product to anybody.</p>

<br>


<h3>5. Have fun.</h3>

<p>When you&rsquo;re relaxed, open to anything, and are working with an awesome team, you can&rsquo;t lose. If we had known at the beginning of the weekend that we would be presenting our product to a panel of VCs and hundreds of other developers we would have stayed later every night, worked harder, argued longer, and in general stressed ourselves out. Instead we just built something cool, and had fun doing it.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a <a href="https://twitter.com/Jason/status/399776123892293632">vine of our team</a> presenting&hellip;</p>

<p>A <a href="http://launch.co/story/team-dom-sawyer-hack-leberry-finn-georgebonnr-kanyang-stephen">shout-out from the @launch folks</a> (I missed the picture)&hellip;</p>

<p>And a <a href="http://launch.co/story/and-the-grand-prize-winners-of-the-launch-hackathon-are-5th">wrap-up message</a> from Jason Calcanis.
Congrats to the top 5 teams – they showcased some amazing products and I can&rsquo;t wait to see what they do next!</p>

<p>If you have any questions about our team, our project, or just want to chat, please drop me a line at <a href="&#x6d;&#97;&#105;&#x6c;&#116;&#x6f;&#58;&#103;&#101;&#111;&#x72;&#103;&#x65;&#98;&#111;&#x6e;&#110;&#x72;&#x40;&#x67;&#x6d;&#x61;&#105;&#x6c;&#46;&#99;&#x6f;&#109;">&#x67;&#101;&#111;&#114;&#103;&#101;&#x62;&#x6f;&#110;&#x6e;&#x72;&#64;&#x67;&#x6d;&#97;&#105;&#x6c;&#46;&#x63;&#111;&#109;</a>.  We&rsquo;re always looking to make new friends!</p>

<br>


<hr />

<h3>Other stuff I&rsquo;ve been working on:</h3>

<h4>1. An app for real-time crowd-based performance art using sockets, smartphones, visualizers, and audio playgrounds (performance is Nov. 17 here in SF)</h4>

<h4>2. A library for working with webaudio (including pitch detection)</h4>

<h4>3. Building a personal site with angular, intention.js, and lots of love.</h4>

<p>Check back soon for posts on these!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
